<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Pathfinder>
  
  <Languages id="Languages">
    
    <Language Name="Common">
      <Description>A common dialect that all creatures speak</Description>
    </Language>
    
    <Language Name="Dwarven">
      <Description>Common dialect among dwarves.</Description>
    </Language>
    
  </Languages>
  
  <Races id="Races">

    <Race Name="Dwarves">
      <Description> Dwarves are a stoic but stern race, enscornced in cities carved from the hearts of mountains and fiercely determined to repel the depredations of savage races like orcs and goblins.  More than any other race, the dwarves have acquired a reputation as dour and humorless that craftsmen of the earth.  It could be said that dwarven history shapes the dark disposition of many dwarves, for they reside in high mountains and dangerous realms below the earch, constantly at war with giants, goblins, and other such horrors</Description>
      <PhysicalDescription> Dwarves are a short and stocky race, and stand about a foot shorter than most humans, with wide, compact bodies that account for their burly appearance.  Male and female dwarves pride themselves on the length of their hair, and men often decorate their beards with a variety of clasps and intricate braids.  A clean-shaven male dwarf is a sure sign of madness, or worse--no one familiar with their race trusts a beardless dwarf.</PhysicalDescription>
      <Society> The great distances between their mountain citadels account for many of the cultural differences that exist within dwarven society.  Despite these schisms, dwarves throughout the world are characterized by their love of stonework, their passion for stone-and metal-based craftsmanship and architecture, and a fierce hatred of giants, orcs, and goblinoids.</Society>
      <Relations> Dwarves and orcs have long dwelt in proximity, theirs a history of violence as old as both races.  Dwarves generally distrust and shun half-orcs.  They find halflings, elves, and gnomes to be too frail, flighty, or "pretty" to be worthy of proper respect.  It is with humans that dwarves share the strongest link, for humans' industrious nature and hearty appetites come closest to matching those of the dwarven ideal.</Relations>
      <AlignmentReligion> Dwarves are driven by honor and tradition, and while they are often satirized as standoffish, they have a strong sense of friendship and justice, and those who win their trust understand that, while they work hard, they play even harder--especially when good ale is involved.  Most dwarves are lawful good.  They prefer to worship deities whose tenets match these traits, and Torag is a favorite among dwarves, though abadar and Gorum are common choices as well.</AlignmentReligion>
      <Adventurers> Although dwarven adventurers are rare compared to humans, they can be found in most regions of the world.  Dwarves often leave the confines of their redoubts to seek glory for their clans, to find wealth with which to enrich the fortress-home of their birth, or to reclaim fallen dwarven citadels from racial enemies.  Dwarven warfare is often characterized by tunnel fighting and melee combat, and as such most dwarves tend toward classes such as fighters and barbarians.</Adventurers>
      <Names>
        <Names gender="Male">
          <Name>Dolgrin</Name>
          <Name>Grunyar</Name>
          <Name>Harsk</Name>
          <Name>Kazmuk</Name>
          <Name>Morgrym</Name>
          <Name>Rogar</Name>
        </Names>
        <Names gender="Female">
          <Name>Agna</Name>
          <Name>Bodill</Name>
          <Name>Ingra</Name>
          <Name>Kotri</Name>
          <Name>Rusilka</Name>
          <Name>Yangrit</Name>
        </Names>
      </Names>
      <Attributes>
        <Description>Dwarves are both tough and wise, but also a bit gruff.</Description>
        <Constitution>2</Constitution>
        <Wisdom>2</Wisdom>
        <Charisma>-2</Charisma>
      </Attributes>
      <Size>Medium</Size>
      <Languages>
        <Language Name="Common"></Language>
        <Language Name="Dwarven"></Language>
        <Modifier> Dwarves with high Intelligence scores can choose from the following: Giant, Gnome, Goblin, Orc, Terran, and Undercommon.</Modifier>
      </Languages>
      <Speed>20</Speed>
      <SpecialAbilities>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Slow and Steady"> Dwarves have a base speed of 20 feet, but their speed is never modified by armor or encumbrance.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Darkvision">Dwarves can see in the dark up to 60 feet.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Defensive Training">Dwarves get a +4 dodge bonus to AC against monsters of the giant subtype.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Greed">Dwarves receive a +2 racial bonus on Appraise skill checks made to determine the price of nonmagical good that contain precious metals or gemstones.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Hatred">Dwarves receive a +1 bonus on attack rolls against humanoid creatures of the orc and goblinoid subtypes due to special training against these hated foes.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Hardy">Dwarves receive a +2 racial bonus on saving throws against poision, spells, and spell-like abilities.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Stability">Dwarves receive a +4 racial bonus to their combat Maneuver Defense when resisting a bull rush or trip attempt while standing on the ground.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Stonecunning">Dwarves receive a +2 bonus on Perception checks to potentially notice unusual stonework, such as traps and hidden doors located in stone walls or floors.  They receive a check to notice such features when they pass within 10 feet of them, whether or not they are actively looking.</SpecialAbility>
      </SpecialAbilities>
      <WeaponProficiencies>
        <WeaponProficiency Name="Battleaxes"></WeaponProficiency>
        <WeaponProficiency Name="Heavy Picks"></WeaponProficiency>
        <WeaponProficiency Name="Warhammers"></WeaponProficiency>
      </WeaponProficiencies>
    </Race>

    <Race Name="Elves">
      <Description> The long-lived elves are children of the natural world, similar in many superficial ways to fey creatures, yet different as well.  Elves value their privacy and traditions, and while they are often slow to make friends, at both the personal and national levels, once an outsider is accepted as comrade, such alliances can last for generations.  Elves have a curious attachment to their surroundings, perhaps as a result of their incredibly long lifespans or some deeper, more mystical reason.  Elves who dwell in a region for long find themselves physically adapting to match their surroundings, most noticeably taking on coloration reflecting the local environment.  Those elves that spend their lives among the short-lived races, on the other hand, often develop a skewed perception of mortality and become morose, the result of warching wave after wave of companions age and die before their eyes.</Description>
      <PhysicalDescription> Dwarves are a short and stocky race, and stand about a foot shorter than most humans, with wide, compact bodies that account for their burly appearance.  Male and female dwarves pride themselves on the length of their hair, and men often decorate their beards with a variety of clasps and intricate braids.  A clean-shaven male dwarf is a sure sign of madness, or worse--no one familiar with their race trusts a beardless dwarf.</PhysicalDescription>
      <Society> The great distances between their mountain citadels account for many of the cultural differences that exist within dwarven society.  Despite these schisms, dwarves throughout the world are characterized by their love of stonework, their passion for stone-and metal-based craftsmanship and architecture, and a fierce hatred of giants, orcs, and goblinoids.</Society>
      <Relations> Dwarves and orcs have long dwelt in proximity, theirs a history of violence as old as both races.  Dwarves generally distrust and shun half-orcs.  They find halflings, elves, and gnomes to be too frail, flighty, or "pretty" to be worthy of proper respect.  It is with humans that dwarves share the strongest link, for humans' industrious nature and hearty appetites come closest to matching those of the dwarven ideal.</Relations>
      <AlignmentReligion> Dwarves are driven by honor and tradition, and while they are often satirized as standoffish, they have a strong sense of friendship and justice, and those who win their trust understand that, while they work hard, they play even harder--especially when good ale is involved.  Most dwarves are lawful good.  They prefer to worship deities whose tenets match these traits, and Torag is a favorite among dwarves, though abadar and Gorum are common choices as well.</AlignmentReligion>
      <Adventurers> Although dwarven adventurers are rare compared to humans, they can be found in most regions of the world.  Dwarves often leave the confines of their redoubts to seek glory for their clans, to find wealth with which to enrich the fortress-home of their birth, or to reclaim fallen dwarven citadels from racial enemies.  Dwarven warfare is often characterized by tunnel fighting and melee combat, and as such most dwarves tend toward classes such as fighters and barbarians.</Adventurers>
      <Names>
        <Names gender="Male">
          <Name>Dolgrin</Name>
          <Name>Grunyar</Name>
          <Name>Harsk</Name>
          <Name>Kazmuk</Name>
          <Name>Morgrym</Name>
          <Name>Rogar</Name>
        </Names>
        <Names gender="Female">
          <Name>Agna</Name>
          <Name>Bodill</Name>
          <Name>Ingra</Name>
          <Name>Kotri</Name>
          <Name>Rusilka</Name>
          <Name>Yangrit</Name>
        </Names>
      </Names>
      <Attributes>
        <Description>Dwarves are both tough and wise, but also a bit gruff.</Description>
        <Constitution>2</Constitution>
        <Wisdom>2</Wisdom>
        <Charisma>-2</Charisma>
      </Attributes>
      <Size>Medium</Size>
      <Languages>
        <Language Name="Common"></Language>
        <Language Name="Dwarven"></Language>
        <Modifier> Dwarves with high Intelligence scores can choose from the following: Giant, Gnome, Goblin, Orc, Terran, and Undercommon.</Modifier>
      </Languages>
      <Speed>20</Speed>
      <SpecialAbilities>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Slow and Steady"> Dwarves have a base speed of 20 feet, but their speed is never modified by armor or encumbrance.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Darkvision">Dwarves can see in the dark up to 60 feet.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Defensive Training">Dwarves get a +4 dodge bonus to AC against monsters of the giant subtype.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Greed">Dwarves receive a +2 racial bonus on Appraise skill checks made to determine the price of nonmagical good that contain precious metals or gemstones.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Hatred">Dwarves receive a +1 bonus on attack rolls against humanoid creatures of the orc and goblinoid subtypes due to special training against these hated foes.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Hardy">Dwarves receive a +2 racial bonus on saving throws against poision, spells, and spell-like abilities.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Stability">Dwarves receive a +4 racial bonus to their combat Maneuver Defense when resisting a bull rush or trip attempt while standing on the ground.</SpecialAbility>
        <SpecialAbility Name="Stonecunning">Dwarves receive a +2 bonus on Perception checks to potentially notice unusual stonework, such as traps and hidden doors located in stone walls or floors.  They receive a check to notice such features when they pass within 10 feet of them, whether or not they are actively looking.</SpecialAbility>
      </SpecialAbilities>
      <WeaponProficiencies>
        <WeaponProficiency Name="Battleaxes"></WeaponProficiency>
        <WeaponProficiency Name="Heavy Picks"></WeaponProficiency>
        <WeaponProficiency Name="Warhammers"></WeaponProficiency>
      </WeaponProficiencies>
    </Race>

  </Races>

  <Classes id="Classes">

    <Class Name="Barbarian">
      <Description>For some, there is only rage.  In the ways of their people, in the fury of their passion, in the howl of battle, conflict is all these brutal souls know.  Savages, hired muscle, masters of vicious martial techniques, they are not soldiers or professional warriors--they are the battle possessed, creatures of slaughter and spirits of war.  Known as barbarians, these warmongers know little of training, preparation, or fules of warfare; for them, only the moment exists, with the foes that stand before them and the knowledge that the next moment might hold their death.  They possess a sixth sense in regard to danger and the endurance to weather all that might entail.  These brutal warriors might rise from all walks of life, both civilized and savage, though whole societies embracing such philosophies roam the wild places of the world.  Within barbarians storms the primal spirit of battle, and woe to those who face their rage.</Description>
      <Role>Barbarians excel in combat, possessing the martial prowess and fortitude to take on foes seemingly far superior to themselves.  With rage granting them boldness and daring beyond that of most other warriors, barbarians charge furiously into battle and ruin all who would stand in their way.</Role>
      <Alignment>nonlawful</Alignment>
      <HitDice>d12</HitDice>
      <ClassSkills>
        <ClassSkill Name="Acrobatics"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Climb"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Craft"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Handle Animal"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Intimidate"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Knowledge_Nature"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Perception"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Ride"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Survival"></ClassSkill>
        <ClassSkill Name="Swim"></ClassSkill>
      </ClassSkills>
      <SkillRanksPerLevel>4 plus Intelligence modifier</SkillRanksPerLevel>
      <WeaponProficiencies>
        <WeaponProficiency Name="Simple"></WeaponProficiency>
        <WeaponProficiency Name="Martial"></WeaponProficiency>
      </WeaponProficiencies>
      <ArmorProficiencies>
        <ArmorProficieny Name="Light"></ArmorProficieny>
        <ArmorProficieny Name="Medium"></ArmorProficieny>
        <ArmorProficieny Name="Shields"></ArmorProficieny>
        <ArmorProficieny Name="Not Tower Shields"></ArmorProficieny>
      </ArmorProficiencies>
      <MovementModifier>10x when wearing No armor, light, or medium armor, and does not have a Heavy Load</MovementModifier>
    </Class>

  </Classes>

</Pathfinder>